{
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Linear_Algebra — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Linear_Algebra — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Two eigen values of a 3x3 real matrix P are (2+\\(\\sqrt{-1}\\)) and 3.The determinantof P is __________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "15",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39634/gate2016-1-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>If the following system has non-trivial solution,<br> px+qy+rz=0 <br> qx+ry+pz=0 <br> rx+py+qz=0,<br> then which one of the following options is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>p-q+r=0 or p=q=-r</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>p+q-r=0 or p=-q=r</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>p+q+r=0 or p=q=r</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>p-q+r=0 or p=-q=-r</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>p+q+r=0 or p=q=r</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8490/gate2015-3-42#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>In the given matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; -1&amp;2 \\\\ 0&amp; 1 &amp; 0\\\\ 1&amp;2 &amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\), one of the eigenvalues is 1. The eigenvectors corresponding to the eigenvalue 1 are <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>{\\(\\alpha (4,2,1)|\\alpha \\neq 0,\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{R}\\)}</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{\\(\\alpha (-4,2,1)|\\alpha \\neq 0,\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{R}\\)}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>{\\(\\alpha (\\sqrt{2},0,1)|\\alpha \\neq 0,\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{R}\\)}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>{\\(\\alpha (-\\sqrt{2},0,1)|\\alpha \\neq 0,\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{R}\\)}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>{\\(\\alpha (-4,2,1)|\\alpha \\neq 0,\\alpha \\in \\mathbb{R}\\)}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8411/gate2015-3-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Perform the following operations on the matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 3 &amp; 4&amp;45 \\\\ 7&amp; 9&amp; 105\\\\ 13&amp;2 &amp; 195 \\end{bmatrix}\\). <br> (i) Add the third row to the second row <br>(ii) Subtract the third column from the first column. <br>The determinant of the resultant matrix is___________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8131/gate2015-2-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The larger of the two eigenvalues of the matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 4 &amp; 5\\\\ 2&amp;1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) is _______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "6",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8051/gate2015-2-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following 2x2 matrix A where two elements are unknown and are marked by a and b. The eigenvalues of this matrix are -1 and 7. What are the values of a and b? <br>\\(A=\\begin{pmatrix} 1 &amp; 4\\\\ b&amp;a \\end{pmatrix}\\). <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a = 6, b = 4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a = 4, b = 6</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a = 3, b = 5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>a = 5, b =3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>a = 5, b =3</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8285/gate2015-1-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>In the LU decomposition of the matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 2 &amp; 2\\\\ 4&amp;9 \\end{bmatrix}\\), if the diagonal elements of U are both 1, then the lower diagonal entry \\(l_{22}\\) of L is________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8241/gate2015-1-23#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The rank of the matrix \\(A=\\left(\\begin{array}{cccc} 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 1 &amp; -1 \\\\ 9 &amp; 5 &amp; 2 &amp; 2 \\\\ 7 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 4 \\end{array}\\right)\\)  is ____ . <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52799/isro2014-72\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Let A be a square matrix size n x n. Consider the following pseudocode. What is the\nexpected output?<pre><code> C = 100;\nfor i = 1 to n do\n   for j = 1 to n do\n   {\n      Temp = A[ i ] [ j ] + C ;\n      A [ i ] [ j ] = A [ j ] [ i ] ;\n      A [ j ] [ i ] = Temp - C ;\n   }\nfor i = 1 to n do\n    for j = 1 to n do\n         output (A[ i ] [ j ]); </code></pre> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The matrix A itself</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Transpose of the matrix A</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Adding 100 to the upper diagonal elements and subtracting 100 from lower diagonal elements of A</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>The matrix A itself</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2044/gate2014-3-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>If V1 and V2 are 4-dimensional subspaces of a 6-dimensional vector space V, then the smallest possible dimension of  V1\\(\\cap\\)V2 is _______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "2",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2039/gate2014-3-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following statements is TRUE about every n x n matrix with only real\neigenvalues? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>If the trace of the matrix is positive and the determinant of the matrix is negative, at least one of its eigenvalues is negative.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If the trace of the matrix is positive, all its eigenvalues are positive.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>If the determinant of the matrix is positive, all its eigenvalues are positive.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>If the product of the trace and determinant of the matrix is positive, all its eigenvalues are positive.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>If the trace of the matrix is positive and the determinant of the matrix is negative, at least one of its eigenvalues is negative.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2038/gate2014-3-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>The product of the non-zero eigenvalues of the matrix <br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0&amp;0 &amp; 0&amp;1 \\\\ 0&amp; 1&amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 0\\\\ 0&amp; 1&amp; 1&amp; 1&amp;0 \\\\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 0\\\\ 1&amp;0 &amp; 0&amp;0 &amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br> is_______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "6",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2013/gate2014-2-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>A non-zero polynomial f(x) of degree 3 has roots at x = 1,x = 2 and x = 3. Which one of the following must be TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f(0)f(4) \\lt 0\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(f(0)f(4) \\gt 0\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(f(0)+f(4) \\gt 0\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(f(0)+f(4) \\lt 0\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f(0)f(4) \\lt 0\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1957/gate2014-2-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>If the matrix A is such that  <br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 2\\\\ -4\\\\ 7 \\end{bmatrix}\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;9 &amp;5 \\end{bmatrix}\\) <br> Then the determinant of A is equal to ________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1956/gate2014-2-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>A function f(x) is continuous in the interval [0,2]. It is known that f(0)=f(2)=-1 and f(1)=1.\nWhich one of the following statements must be true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>There exists a y in the interval (0,1) such that f(y)=f(y+1)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>For every y in the interval (0,1), f(y)=f(2-y)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The maximum value of the function in the interval (0.2) is 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>There exists a y in the interval (0,1) such that f(y)=-f(2-y)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>There exists a y in the interval (0,1) such that f(y)=f(y+1)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1925/gate2014-1-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}